<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="documentation">
    <div>
        <head>The corpus</head>
        <p>The project ANTONOMAZ, in collaboration with the Bibliothèque Mazarine, aims to encode
            the Mazarinades's corpus in order to integrate it to a database usable by different
            audiences (researchers, students...) and to allow it to be studied. The Mazarinades are
            a serie of textual sources of different genres (pamphlets, poems, letters, etc.)
            published during the Fronde (1648 - 1653) mostly against the Cardinal Jules Mazarin. The
            project uses the works of Célestin Moreau (Bibliographie des Mazarinades), Emile Socard,
            Ernest Labadie and of Hubert Carrier (Presses de la Fronde). In addition, the project
            wishes to find sources not registered by any of these bibliographers to get a corpus as
            exhaustive as possible. We encoded fac-similes from these digital libraries: <list>
                <item>Gallica (Bibliothèque Nationale de France)</item>
                <item>Mazarinum (Bibliothèque Mazarine)</item>
                <item>Google Books</item>
            </list></p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Document identifiers</head>
        <div>
            <head>Identifying the document</head>
            <p>One of our priorities is to clearly identify the text once encoded. We chose to give
                to each document an unique identifier consisting of the name of the digital library
                where the document was founded and its digital permanent identifier. So, for a
                gallica's one, it will be<code>Moreau1234_GALL</code>. The filename will match with
                the xml:id. This is going to be modified in the future. Here is the list for the
                different possibilities in naming documents: <list>
                    <item>mazarinum: Moreau1234_MAZ</item>
                    <item>gallica: Moreau1234_GALL</item>
                    <item>Google Books: Moreau1234_GALL</item>
                </list> If the text comes from Carrier, Labadie or Socard, replace "Moreau" by the
                right name. If your text is registered in one of Moreau's supplements, the
                identifier will be: <code>Moreau1suppl12_GALL</code>. You can translate it like
                this: Moreau, first supplement, 12th in the list, from gallica. If your document is
                inside a collection, the identifier must be: "Moreau115pp.31-38_GALL". </p>
            <p>In addition, each document will get a <att>type</att> inside the <gi>TEI</gi>
                declaration which corresponds to the corpus it belongs to. For example, if the text
                is a burlesque mazarinade, write "Mazarinade_burlesque".</p>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>The encoding</head>
            <div>
                <head>Headers encoding</head>
                <p>The header contains: a <gi>fileDesc</gi>, an <gi>encodingDesc</gi> and a
                        <gi>profileDesc</gi>.</p>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <!-- Camille : à changer pour mettre un lien vers nos propres exemples -->
                    <teiHeader>
                        <fileDesc>
                            <!-- information about the encoded document -->
                        </fileDesc>
                        <encodingDesc>
                            <!-- Some general informations about the encoding's choices -->
                        </encodingDesc>
                        <profileDesc>
                            <!-- Contains general informations about the encoded document: the language in which it's written, its genre, etc. -->
                        </profileDesc>
                    </teiHeader>
                </egXML>
                <div>
                    <head>The <gi>fileDesc</gi></head>
                    <p>This part of the header contains four parts : <list>
                            <item>the <gi>titleStmt</gi></item>
                            <item>the <gi>respStmt</gi></item>
                            <item>the <gi>publicationStmt</gi></item>
                            <item>the <gi>sourceDesc</gi></item>
                        </list></p>
                    <div>
                        <head>The <gi>titleStmt</gi></head>
                        <p>This part is essential for the presentation of the encoded document. It
                            has to contain two <gi>titles</gi> : a main <gi>title</gi> (source's
                            title) and a sub <gi>title</gi> (ANTONOMAZ édition).</p>
                        <p>The main <gi>title</gi> has a <gi>source</gi> attribute filled by default
                            by "Moreau". If it's possible to get the Mazarinum's title, take it and
                            replace "Moreau" by "BM". The same operation will have to be done for
                            the <gi>title</gi> the <gi>bibl</gi></p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <titleStmt>
                                <title type="main">Visions astrologiques de Michel Nostradamus sur
                                    toutes les affaires de ce temps, et la confusion de Mazarin. En
                                    vers burlesques</title>
                                <title type="sub">ANTONOMAZ édition</title>
                            </titleStmt>
                        </egXML>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The <gi>respStmt</gi></head>
                        <p>This part contains the list of persons having worked on the document's
                            encoding. It is necessary to indicate a <gi>persName</gi> with a
                                <att>role</att> attribute and an <gi>affiliation</gi> and the ORCID
                            number (if there is one) for each person, encoded inside a
                                <att>ref</att>. If the person gets an ORCID number, don't indicate
                            the affiliation since the information is already contained inside the
                            ORCID's database.</p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <persName role="Chef_projet">
                                <forename>Karine</forename>
                                <surname>Abiven</surname>
                                <idno>0000-0001-9518-1040</idno>
                            </persName>
                        </egXML>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The <gi>publicationStmt</gi></head>
                        <p>This part contains always the <gi>publisher</gi>, a <gi>date</gi> for the
                            file's creation and eventually its correction, as well as the
                                <gi>availibility</gi> which contains the <gi>licence</gi>. In our
                            project, this part is always the same.</p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <publicationStmt>
                                <publisher>Projet ANTONOMAZ / Sorbonne Université</publisher>
                                <ref target="https://github.com/Antonomaz"/>
                                <date type="file_creation" when="2026-04-20">26 avril 2021</date>
                                <availability status="restricted" n="cc-by">
                                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"/>
                                </availability>
                            </publicationStmt>
                        </egXML>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The <gi>sourceDesc</gi></head>
                        <p>This part contains one element: the <gi>bibl</gi>. It gets the following
                            elements: <list>
                                <item><gi>ref</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>author</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>persName</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>title</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>pubPlace</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>publisher</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>date</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>extent</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>note</gi></item>
                                <item><gi>ref</gi></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>About the first element <gi>ref</gi>: in the attribute <att>target</att>,
                            copy only the link to the fac-simile.</p>
                        <p>Specifications about the element <gi>author</gi></p>
                        <p>If the author is not certain, add:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>@type:"alleged_author"</item>
                            <item>@source: "Name of the attributor (a person, an
                                institution...)"</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>If the author is a faked one, add: a @type:"faked_author"</p>
                        <p>About the element <gi>date</gi>: if someone dated the document -the date
                            was not inscribed on the original document - give the identity of the
                            attributor like this: @source:"Name of the attributor"</p>
                        <p>Each author will get an isni's number (if there is one), encoded in a
                                <att>ref</att> attribute.</p>
                        <p>About the element <gi>note</gi>: there is three <att>type</att>: <list>
                                <item>"format" : the document's format.</item>
                                <item>"Bibliographer's name_identifier": each document has an unique
                                    number. If we say "3600", it means it's the 3600th document in
                                    the Bibliographie. If the bibliographer is Moreau, write
                                    "Moreau_identifier".</item>
                                <item>"BM_identifier" : identifier from mazarinum (the Bibliothèque
                                    Mazarine's digital library)</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>About the element <gi>persName</gi>: it is meant for recipients and
                            dedicatees only. It gets two attributes:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item><att>role</att> which is filled by "received".</item>
                            <item><att>ref</att> which is filled by an isni's number.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>If your author or recipient is a noble, do not write its titles. The
                            information is already contained inside the isni's database.</p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <persName role="received" ref="isni:0000000121336441">
                                <forename>Gaston</forename>
                                <surname>France (De)</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </egXML>
                        <p>If your <gi>author</gi> is anonymus, remove <gi>persName</gi> element and
                            just fill <gi>author</gi> with "Anonyme".</p>
                        <p>If you have multiple authors, duplicate the <gi>author</gi> element as
                            much as needed.</p>
                        <p>If you have no <gi>placeName</gi>, remove the <att>ref</att> and
                                <att>source</att> attributes from the element and write "Sans
                            Lieu".</p>
                        <p>In some cases, the placeName inscribed on the document is fake. So, it is
                            necessary to indicate the false placeName in a first <gi>pubPlace</gi>
                            element and then the true one in another <gi>placeName</gi> element.</p>
                        <p>If you have no publisher, remove the <att>ref</att> and <att>source</att>
                            attributes from the element and write "Sans Nom".</p>
                        <p>About the second <gi>ref</gi> element: it contains a <att>type</att>
                            filled with "BM_notice". In the <att>target</att>, copy only the link to
                            the Mazarine's notice.</p>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                    <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k118539m"/>
                                    <title source="BM">Visions astrologiques de Michel Nostradamus
                                        sur toutes les affaires de ce temps. Et la confusion de
                                        Mazarin. En vers burlesques.</title>
                                    <author role="alleged_author" ref="isni:0000000083395220">
                                        <persName>
                                            <forename>Michel</forename>
                                            <surname>Nostradamus</surname>
                                        </persName>
                                    </author>

                                    <pubPlace ref="geonames:2988507">Paris</pubPlace>
                                    <publisher ref="isni:0000000011194155">
                                        <forename>Veuve d'André</forename>
                                        <surname>Musnier</surname>
                                    </publisher>
                                    <date when="1649-01" source="Carrier">Janvier 1649</date>
                                    <extent>
                                        <measure unit="pages" quantity="12"/>
                                    </extent>
                                    <note type="format">in-4</note>
                                    <note type="Moreau_identifier">4038</note>
                                    <note type="BM_identifier">BM00122</note>
                                    <ref type="BM_notice"
                                        target="https://mazarinades.bibliotheque-mazarine.fr/ark:/61562/bm48973"
                                    />
                                </bibl>
                            </sourceDesc>
                        </egXML>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The <gi>msDesc</gi></head>
                        <p>Even if the Mazarinades are, for the most part, printed documents, the
                                <gi>msDesc</gi> was useful to us. To ensure a good encoding, some
                            elements are recommanded : <list>
                                <item><p><gi>msIdentifier</gi> which contains information used to
                                        properly identify the manuscript</p>
                                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                        <msIdentifier>
                                            <settlement>Paris</settlement>
                                            <institution>Bibliothèque Nationale de
                                                France</institution>
                                            <repository>Réserve des livres rares</repository>
                                            <idno type="cote">YE-4819</idno>
                                        </msIdentifier>
                                    </egXML>
                                </item>
                                <item><gi>history</gi> which contains information about the history
                                    of the manuscript. We used it to report the presence or absence
                                    of a stamp with a boolean (true or false). True is valid for any
                                    stamp, the ones from the library keeping the physical copy
                                    included. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                        <history>
                                            <provenance>
                                                <stamp>False</stamp>
                                            </provenance>
                                        </history>
                                    </egXML></item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The <gi>encodingDesc</gi></head>
                <p>This part contains some general informations about the project and the documents'
                    encoding. It uses the following elements: <list>
                        <item><gi>projectDesc</gi></item>
                        <item><gi>editorialDecl</gi></item>
                    </list></p>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <encodingDesc>
                        <projectDesc>
                            <p> Cette édition a été réalisée dans le cadre du projet ANTONOMAZ. Son
                                objectif principal est de fournir un texte destiné à l'exploration
                                avec des outils électroniques. De ce fait, ce n'est ni une édition
                                philologique, ni une édition pédagogique ou de redécouverte d'un
                                auteur oublié. </p>
                            <p> Les textes encodés dans le cadre du projet ANTONOMAZ sont issus de
                                numérisations de bibliothèques numériques publiques et de Google
                                livres. </p>
                            <p> L'édition présentée ici est issue d'un processus d'OCRisation
                                réalisé avec Kraken. </p>
                        </projectDesc>
                        <editorialDecl>
                            <correction>
                                <p> Les erreurs typographiques ont été signalées à l'aide des
                                    éléments sic et corr </p>
                            </correction>
                            <normalization>
                                <p> La transcription est la plus diplomatique possible.</p>
                                <p>Les graphie et orthographe d'origine ont été respectées, y
                                    compris lettres non dissimilées : ij/uv,'s' longs, et
                                    abréviations. </p>
                            </normalization>
                            <hyphenation>
                                <p> Les vers ont été représentés à l'aide des éléments l et lb. Les
                                    strophes ont été représentées à l'aide de l'élément lg. </p>
                                <p> Les textes en prose ont été redécoupés à l'aide de l'élément lb.
                                    Les paragraphes ont été signalés à l'aide de l'élément p. </p>
                                <p> La division des mots en fin de ligne respecte le fac-similé
                                    original. Elle est signalée par l'attribut "break" et "¬". </p>
                            </hyphenation>
                            <punctuation>
                                <p> La ponctuation d'origine a été respectée, y compris quand elle
                                    paraissait fautive, alors signalée à l'aide des éléments sic et
                                    corr </p>
                            </punctuation>
                        </editorialDecl>
                    </encodingDesc>
                </egXML>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The <gi>profileDesc</gi></head>
                <p>This part describes non bibliographical informations.</p>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <profileDesc>
                        <langUsage>
                            <language ident="fr">Document en français</language>
                        </langUsage>
                        <abstract>
                            <p source="BM_notes">En vers, les "visions" sont en quatrains
                                d'alexandrins, "La confusion de Mazarin", en dizains d'octosyllabes.
                                Texte paru en janvier 1649 d’après Hubert Carrier (Bibliothèque
                                Mazarine, Ms 4682-2, f. 406v). </p>
                        </abstract>
                        <textClass>
                            <keywords>
                                <term type="form">vers</term>
                                <term type="genre">poésie</term>
                                <term type="subgenre">burlesque</term>
                                <term type="subgenre">satirique</term>
                                <term type="subject"/>
                            </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                    </profileDesc>
                </egXML>
                <p>Concerning the <gi>abstract</gi>, this element serves to indicate notes from
                    different libraries about the document or from the Antonomaz team. This part is
                    essential since it can give precious information about the text to the audience.
                    We have different abbreviations for each library or projects: <list><item>BM:
                            Bibliothèque Mazarine</item>
                        <item>BML: Bibliothèque municipale de Lyon</item>
                        <item>BnF: Bibliothèque nationale de France</item>
                        <item>BL: The British Library</item>
                        <item>BnA: Bibliothèque nationale d'Autriche</item>
                        <item>BEB: Bibliothèque de l'Etat de Bavière</item>
                        <item>BncF: Bibliothèque nationale centrale de Florence</item>
                        <item>Antonomaz: Antonomaz project.</item></list></p>
                <p>You can add libraries to the list, but do not forget to indicate the abbreviation
                    here so everyone can follow your lead.</p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div>
            <div>
                <head>Text encoding</head>
                <p>We have chosen to divide our encoding into steps. The first one is to get the
                    cleanest metadata. Consequently, we have decided for a very simple first
                    encoding of the text's body. In our corpus, however, some documents are
                    different from the others, with a richer text's body's encoding: this is the
                    result of our work before taking the decision to make metadata our main priority
                    for the moment. So, we will describe the two states of encoding.</p>

                <div>
                    <head>Simple encoding</head>
                    <p>First, at all levels our edition must contain a <gi>text</gi> element with
                        the following namespace : @xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0". It checks
                        the validation of the TEI schema.</p>
                    <p>Then, we use the element <gi>body</gi>with: <list><item><gi>p</gi> for prose
                                parts. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <text>
                                        <body>
                                            <p>
                                                <pb n="1"/>
                                                <lb/>oogps <lb/>RELATION <lb/>E CE QVI SEST PASSE’
                                                <lb/>EN LA VILLE <lb/>DE PERONNE <lb/>Sur le refus
                                                que les Habitans ont <lb/>fait dereceuoir &amp;
                                                d’ouuir leurs <lb/>portes au Mareſchal
                                                <lb/>d’Hoquincourt leur <lb/>Gouuerneur. <lb/> aa?
                                                <lb/>S4 <lb/>A PARI S <lb/>a e nvlr ee! <lb/> uu u
                                                vieili oaue le¬ <pb n="2"/>
                                                <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/>¬¬ <lb/>
                                                <lb/> , <lb/> 1 <lb/>¬ ¬ <lb/>
                                                <lb/>o a <lb/> . <lb/> d <lb/>aa <lb/>a. <lb/>E
                                                <lb/>3 <lb/>oioqe <pb n="3"/>
                                                <lb/>u&amp;&amp; e,&amp;t,,&amp;, l, <lb/>ede t
                                                <lb/>Relation veritable de ce qui <lb/>s’eſt paſſé
                                                en la ville de Pe¬ <lb/>ronne, &amp; du refus que
                                                ſes <lb/>Habitans ont fait d’ouurir <lb/>leurs
                                                portes au Mareſchal <lb/>d’Hoquincourt leur Gou¬
                                                <lb/>uerneur. <lb/> NE Ville frontiere, &amp; qui
                                                eſt <lb/> expoſée à l’ennemy voiln, ne <lb/>ſJ peut
                                                eſtre trop bien gardée, &amp; <lb/>I ny a heure au
                                                iour ny en la <lb/> nuict, à laquelle il ne faille
                                                <lb/> x qui y frequentent, coniderer <lb/>leurs
                                                actions &amp; ſçauoir le ſujet pourquoy ils y
                                                <lb/>ſejounent, il faut auſſi prendre garde à ceux
                                                qui <lb/> yentrent &amp; qui en ſortent, foü̈iller
                                                les charettes <lb/> &amp; charioss qui y arriuenr,
                                                pour voir s’il ny a rien <lb/>de caché, qui puiſſe
                                                nuire à la ville, comme. <lb/>venant de la part de
                                                l’ennemy, qui muguette tou¬ <lb/>ſiours la place
                                                frontiere qui luy eſt proche, &amp; <lb/> ploye tous
                                                les artifices &amp; ſtraragémes, pour <lb/>taſcher
                                                à la ſurprendre. <lb/>Sil ya des garniſons, il faut
                                                ſoigneuſement</p>
                                        </body>
                                    </text>
                                </egXML>
                            </item>
                            <item><gi>l</gi> for versified parts. <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <text>
                                        <body>
                                            <l>
                                                <lb/> Qui me ſont aparus dedans mes viſions, </l>
                                            <l>
                                                <lb/> Si vous n'entendez bien le langage des Anges, </l>
                                            <l>
                                                <lb/> Vous trouuerez icy bien des deciſions. </l>
                                        </body>
                                    </text>
                                </egXML>
                            </item>
                            <item><gi>lb</gi> for line beginning.</item></list></p>
                </div>



                <div>
                    <head>Richer encoding</head>
                    <p>We use the element <gi>body</gi> with: <list>
                            <item><gi>head</gi>: contains the elements <gi>pb</gi> for page
                                beginning with a link pointing towards the right page on the
                                fac-simile, <gi>title</gi> for the title on the front page,
                                    <gi>ref</gi> which contains a link to the printer mark and
                                    <gi>note</gi> for edition's informations.</item>
                            <item><gi>pb</gi> for page beginning.</item>
                            <item><gi>fw</gi> : has three <att>types</att> : "pageNum" for page
                                numbers, "catch" for catches", "sig" for signatures.</item>
                            <item><gi>p</gi> for prose parts.</item>
                            <item><gi>l</gi> for versified parts</item>
                            <item><gi>lg</gi> for a stanza</item>
                            <item><gi>lb</gi> for line beginning. It can get two attributes :
                                    <att>rend</att> and <att>break</att> used for cut words. </item>
                            <item><gi>hi</gi> is used for any graphic distinction</item>
                            <item><gi>sic</gi> reports an error in the original text.</item>
                            <item><gi>corr</gi> indicates a correction made by the editor of the
                                encoded text.</item>
                            <item><gi>foreign</gi> is used to indicate a word or a word group in a
                                language different from the original one. It gets one attribute
                                    <att>xml:lang</att></item>
                            <item><gi>note</gi> to encode any note in the original text. Its
                                location on the page should be indicated with a <att>place</att>.
                            </item>
                        </list></p>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <text>
                            <body>
                                <head>
                                    <pb n="1"
                                        facs="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k118539m/f1.item.r=bpt6k118539m"/>
                                    <pb n="2"
                                        facs="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k118539m/f2.item.r=bpt6k118539m"/>
                                    <title type="main"> VISIONS <lb/> ASTROLOGIQVES <lb/> DE MICHEL
                                        <lb/> NOSTRADAMVS <lb/> ſur toutes les affaires de ce Temps.
                                        <lb/> ET <lb/> LA CONFVSION <lb/> DE MAZARIN <lb/> En Vers
                                        Burleſques. </title>
                                    <ref target="#GALL_bpt6k118539m_1.png">[Marque
                                        imprimeur-libraire]</ref>
                                    <note type="edition"> A PARIS, <lb/> Chez la veſue A. MVSNIER,
                                        au mont ſainct Hilaire, <lb/> en la Court d'Albret. <lb/> M.
                                        DC. XLIX. <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="it">AVEC PERMISSION.</hi>
                                    </note>
                                </head>
                                <p>
                                    <pb n="3"
                                        facs="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k118539m/f3.item.r=bpt6k118539m"/>
                                    <title type="secondary"> LES VISIONS <l>
                                            <lb/> DE MICHEL </l>
                                        <l>
                                            <lb/> NOSTRADAMVS </l>
                                        <l>
                                            <lb/> ſur les affaires du temps preſent. </l>
                                    </title>
                                </p>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <ref target="#GALL_bpt6k118539m_2.png">[Lettrine]</ref>
                                        Vrieux qui voulez voir les choſes eſtranges </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Qui me ſont aparus dedans mes viſions, </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Si vous n'entendez bien le langage des Anges, </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Vous trouuerez icy bien des deciſions. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Le Ciel ce preparant à receuoir les ombres, </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Et le iour declinant faiſant place à la nuict, </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Ce para de ces feux accouſtumez en nombre, </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Ou parmy s’aparut ce qu’icy deſſous ſuit. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Ie vis premierement vne grande iſle verte </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Belle &amp; fertille autant, qu’on puiſſe ſouhaitter </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Qui d’vn lys ſeulement ſembloit eſtre couuerte </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Que pluſieurs animaux vouloient venir gaſter. </l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Entre iceux animaux eſtoit vne grenouille </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Que ie vis accoupler auec vn gras crapaud, </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Qui ſembloient empeſcher que l'iſle l’on ne ſouille: </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Mais ie vis bien apres qu’il eſtoient du trouppeau.
                                    </l>
                                </lg>
                                <pb n="4"
                                    facs="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k118539m/f4.item.r=bpt6k118539m"/>
                                <lg>
                                    <fw place="top-center" type="pageNum">4</fw>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> le les vis approcher de pluſieurs belles ruſches </l>
                                    <l>
                                        <lb/> Leſquelles enuenimerent &amp; mangerent le miel, </l>
                                </lg>
                            </body>
                        </text>
                    </egXML>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
